const history = [{ "question": "In which US state is the active Mount Rainier volcano located?", "category": "history", "answer": "Washington", "choices": ["Michigan", "Ohio", "Washington", "New York"] }, { "question": "In 1990, this 5000 year old body was found in the Alps. Scientists discovered some tattoos on his leg which indicated that acupuncture was used as far back as the Copper-stone Age.", "category": "history", "answer": "Oetzi", "choices": ["Big Foot", "Sasquatch", "Nessie", "Oetzi"] }, { "question": "After unsuccessful  talks about oil production and debt repayment, Iraq occupied Kuwait.  In January 1991 the US launched an air attack against military targets in Iraq and Kuwait in this operation.", "category": "history", "answer": "Desert Storm", "choices": ["Matador", "BOLERO", "Determined Force", "Desert Storm"] }, { "question": "It is the process of producing identical copies of a DNA segment asexually.  In 1996 the first successful one of an animal was made. The animals name was Dolly.  Dolly later died, but Richard Seed announced that he intended try it on humans.", "category": "history", "answer": "Cloning", "choices": ["Organ Transplant", "Cloning", "Bloodless Surgery", "Laser Surgery"] }, { "question": "This kind of music became largely popular in Europe and America in the 1990s. It is a melodic, free form combination between techno and house, having hypnotic qualities. The first distinctive track of this kind was Age Of Love, released in 1990.", "category": "history", "answer": "Trance", "choices": ["Electro", "Trance", "Techno", "Dance"] }, { "question": "This womans death was arguably the most shocking one of the decade. She died in 1997 in a car crash while evading paparazzi. The woman was taken to a hospital, but the two-hour efforts of surgeons to save her life were unsuccessful.", "category": "history", "answer": "Princess Diana", "choices": ["Greta Garbo", "Nancy Marchand", "Madam C. J. Walker", "Princess Diana"] }, { "question": "This union, made up of European countries, was established by the Maastricht Treaty in 1992. Starting as a trade body it is now an economic and political partnership between its members.", "category": "history", "answer": "The European Union", "choices": ["American Labor Union", "Oxford Union", "The European Union", "European Trade Union"] }, { "question": "Although the first one was sent in 1971, it became widely popular in 1998. Its popularity caused explosive growth of the internet.", "category": "history", "answer": "The E-mail", "choices": ["The Chat programs", "The URL", "The E-mail", "The Website"] }, { "question": "Impeachment stands for quickly removing dangerously criminal officials from high office. The Impeachment Trial in the Senate for this US President commenced on January 7, 1999.", "category": "history", "answer": "Bill Clinton", "choices": ["George Bush", "Ronald Reagan", "Bill Clinton", "Richard Nixon"] }, { "question": "On August 17, 1999 this disaster took the lives of 15 000 and injured 23 000 people in western Turkey.", "category": "history", "answer": "Earthquake", "choices": ["Earthquake", "Tsunami", "Avalanche", "Volcano eruption"] }, { "question": "These became more advanced and more popular in the 1990, with some of the most influential ones being  the Super Nintendo Entertainment System, the Sony Playstation, and the Sega Dreamcast.", "category": "history", "answer": "Video Game consoles", "choices": ["Dating sites", "Virtual reality systems", "Video Game consoles", "Computer games"] }, { "question": "The Punic Wars were a series of three wars fought between these two powers.", "category": "history", "answer": "Rome and Carthage", "choices": ["Rome and Athens", "Athens and Sparta", "Carthage and Athens", "Rome and Carthage"] }, { "question": "The 1938 incorporation of Austria in Greater Germany under the Nazi Regime is known as this.", "category": "history", "answer": "Anschluss", "choices": ["Ansatz", "Abwer", "Anschluss", "Ahnentafel"] }, { "question": "Henry Kissinger held this US post from 1974 to 1977.", "category": "history", "answer": "Secretary of State", "choices": ["President of the Senate", "Speaker of the House of Representatives", "National Security Advisor", "Secretary of State"] }, { "question": "One of these cities has been Japans capital in the past.", "category": "history", "answer": "Kyoto", "choices": ["Kyoto", "Yokohama", "Hiroshima", "Osaka"] }, { "question": "Anne of Austria was the mother of Louis XIV of France (the Sun King).", "category": "history", "answer": "True", "choices": ["True", "False"] }, { "question": "Valeria Messalina was the third wife of this Roman emperor.", "category": "history", "answer": "Claudius", "choices": ["Caligula", "Tiberius", "Nero", "Claudius"] }, { "question": "Philip II of France, Richard I of England and Frederick I led this campaign.", "category": "history", "answer": "Third Crusade", "choices": ["Childrens Crusade", "Albigensian Crusade", "Fourth Crusade", "Third Crusade"] }, { "question": "Yu the Great was the legendary first Chinese monarch of this dynasty.", "category": "history", "answer": "Xia Dynasty", "choices": ["Xia Dynasty", "Qing (Manchu) Dynasty", "Ming Dynasty", "Yuan Dynasty"] }, { "question": "This German general was nicknamed The Desert Fox due to the skillful military campaigns he waged in North Africa, during World War II.", "category": "history", "answer": "Erwin Rommel", "choices": ["Erwin Rommel", "Hermann Goring", "George Patton", "Bernard Montgomery"] }, { "question": "The term Blitzkrieg, referring to swift, sudden military offensive, is translated as Thunder War.", "category": "history", "answer": "False", "choices": ["False", "True"] }, { "question": "How many landing beaches were there in the 1944 Normandy Invasion, known as Operation Overlord?", "category": "history", "answer": "Five", "choices": ["Four", "Six", "Five", "Three"] }, { "question": "What was the name of the first jet-powered fighter used in World War II?", "category": "history", "answer": "Me-262", "choices": ["P-51", "Hurricane", "Me-262", "MIG-3"] }, { "question": "Which member of the Nazi Party was known as Adolph Hitlers first architect of the Third Reich?", "category": "history", "answer": "Albert Speer", "choices": ["Rudolph Hess", "Albert Speer", "Hermann Goring", "Joseph Mengele"] }, { "question": "The British evacuation from which French port was codenamed Operation Dynamo, in 1940?", "category": "history", "answer": "Dunkirk", "choices": ["Brest", "Cherbourg", "Dunkirk", "Toulon"] }, { "question": "Which American politician said the following about liberty: They that can give up essential liberty to obtain a little temporary safety deserve neither liberty nor safety.â?", "category": "history", "answer": "Benjamin Franklin", "choices": ["Benjamin Franklin", "Thomas Jefferson", "Abraham Lincoln", "George Washington"] }, { "question": "Which US President delivered the following words: Ask not what your country can do for you, ask what you can do for your country.?", "category": "history", "answer": "John F. Kennedy", "choices": ["William J. Clinton", "Franklin D. Roosevelt", "Abraham Lincoln", "John F. Kennedy"] }, { "question": "Which US President said these words: A democracy is nothing more than mob rule, where fifty-one percent of the people may take away the rights of the other forty-nine.?", "category": "history", "answer": "Thomas Jefferson", "choices": ["Abraham Lincoln", "Thomas Jefferson", "Benjamen Franklin", "John F. Kennedy"] }, { "question": "Which US President made the following statement: America stands for liberty, for the pursuit of happiness and for the unalienable right for life. This right to life cannot be granted or denied by government because it does not come from the government, it comes from the creator of life.?", "category": "history", "answer": "George W. Bush", "choices": ["George W. Bush", "Thomas Jefferson", "John Adams", "George Washington"] }, { "question": "These words were spoken by Jed Babbin, a former deputy undersecretary of defence in the first Bush administration, on January 30, 2003: Going to war without France is like going deer hunting without an accordion. You just leave a lot of useless noisy baggage behind.", "category": "history", "answer": "True", "choices": ["False", "True"] }, { "question": "Which great American leader made the following statement: Any people anywhere, being inclined and having the power, have the right to rise up, and shake off the existing government, and form a new one that suits them better. This is a most valuable - a most sacred right - a right, which we hope and believe, is to liberate the world.â?", "category": "history", "answer": "Abraham Lincoln", "choices": ["Benjamin Franklin", "Abraham Lincoln", "George Washington", "Thomas Jefferson"] }, { "question": "The M1 Carbine is the most mass produced small arm weapon in the United States. Even though it was mainly produced by the Inland Division of General Motors, its design belongs to this famous company.", "category": "history", "answer": "Winchester", "choices": ["Winchester", "Kalashnikov", "GIAT Industries", "Magnum Research Inc."] }, { "question": "How many Medal of Honor citations have been issued during the Vietnam War?", "category": "history", "answer": "245", "choices": ["245", "345", "153", "120"] }, { "question": "One of the worlds greatest generals. By  the age of 30 he ruled almost half of the world. This great leader died at the peak of his campaign at the age of 33.  His was taught by Aristotle.", "category": "history", "answer": "Alexander The Great", "choices": ["Alexander The Great", "Darius", "Julius Caesar", "Augustus"] }, { "question": "This Carthaginian general marched from Spain to Rome across the Alps.  14,000 of his 40,000 troops died because of the harsh climate.  Later, he won the Battle of Cannae.", "category": "history", "answer": "Hannibal", "choices": ["Augustus", "Gaius Marius", "Lesius Quietus", "Hannibal"] }, { "question": "His saying, Veni Vidi Vici (I came I saw I conquered) is known all over the world.  His war feats clothed him with glory giving him political power.", "category": "history", "answer": "Julius Caesar", "choices": ["Marcus Antonius", "Julius Caesar", "Augustus", "Darius"] }, { "question": "This American general  led the invasion of Normandy.  He was also an American president from 1953 to 1961.", "category": "history", "answer": "Dwight Eisenhower", "choices": ["Dwight Eisenhower", "George S. Patton", "MacArthur", "William H. Simpson"] }, { "question": "He was one of the best military officers of Russia during the World War II and involved in the taking of Berlin.", "category": "history", "answer": "Georgi Zhukov", "choices": ["Lavr Kornilov", "Georgi Zhukov", "Alexander Samsonov", "Nicholas Nikolaevich"] }, { "question": "The siege of Leningrad lasted just 1 month.", "category": "history", "answer": "False", "choices": ["True", "False"] }, { "question": "Along with the French general, this British general also led the campaign in Northern Africa during the World War II.  He was accused of not fighting bravely enough, after his lack of success in Operation Lightfoot.", "category": "history", "answer": "Bernard Montgomery", "choices": ["Dwight Eisenhower", "Bernard Montgomery", "Georg Stumme", "John White"] }, { "question": "This island was Englands first overseas colony.", "category": "history", "answer": "Newfoundland", "choices": ["Rhodes", "Newfoundland", "Iceland", "Greenland"] }, { "question": "In 1962 Jamaica gained full independence from the United Kingdom, but before even becoming a British colony, Jamaica was possession of this country.", "category": "history", "answer": "Spain", "choices": ["Spain", "Portugal", "Russia", "Italy"] }, { "question": "Barbados has never been a British colony.", "category": "history", "answer": "False", "choices": ["True", "False"] }, { "question": "Australia was officially settled in 1788 as the penal colony of New South Wales. Over the course of the 19th century this many new self-governing Crown Colonies were established on the continent.", "category": "history", "answer": "5", "choices": ["4", "5", "3", "12"] }, { "question": "One of  the results of the Second Anglo-Dutch War, between England and the United Netherlands, was that the city of New Amsterdam was renamed to this.", "category": "history", "answer": "New York", "choices": ["New York", "New Jersey", "New Mexico", "New Orleans"] }, { "question": "Sri Lanka was not considered part of the British Raj.", "category": "history", "answer": "True", "choices": ["False", "True"] }, { "question": "Slavery was outlawed in all British colonies in this year.", "category": "history", "answer": "1834", "choices": ["1812", "1912", "1834", "1738"] }, { "question": "On July 1, 1997, the former British colony of Hong Kong reunified with the Peoples Republic of China. This man was the last governor of Hong Kong.", "category": "history", "answer": "Chris Patten", "choices": ["Henry Tang", "Chris Patten", "Tung Chee Hwa", "Donald Tsang"] }, { "question": "Britain was not interested in African territories and thus has never controlled any.", "category": "history", "answer": "False", "choices": ["False", "True"] }, { "question": "What was the nickname of Tom Cruises character in Top Gun?", "category": "history", "answer": "Maverick", "choices": ["Goose", "Iceman", "Maverick", "Viper"] }, { "question": "What NBA team won their 16th NBA Championship title on June 8,1986?", "category": "history", "answer": "Boston Celtics", "choices": ["Boston Celtics", "Houston Rockets", "L.A. Lakers", "Chicago Bulls"] }, { "question": "Which of these songs was not on Bon Jovis chart-topping 1986 album Slippery When Wet?", "category": "history", "answer": "Ill Be There for You", "choices": ["Ill Be There for You", "Never Say Goodbye", "Livin on a Prayer", "Wanted Dead Or Alive"] }, { "question": "When this significant event took place on January 28, 1986, students worldwide saw it on live television.", "category": "history", "answer": "Space Shuttle Challenger explodes", "choices": ["A nuclear reactor at the Chernobyl nuclear plant explodes", "Space Shuttle Challenger explodes", "The United States Senate allows its debates to be televised", "Pope John Paul II officially visits the Synagogue of Rome"] }, { "question": "The New York Mets were World Champions in baseball in the 1986 world series.", "category": "history", "answer": "True", "choices": ["False", "True"] }, { "question": "Which one of these actors was not in the Academy Award winning Oliver Stone film Platoon?", "category": "history", "answer": "Tom Cruise", "choices": ["Tom Berenger", "Charlie Sheen", "Johnny Depp", "Tom Cruise"] }, { "question": "On what album released in 1986 would I find the following lyrics:\nWhen I was 17 I did what people told me,\nDid what my father said and let my mother mold me", "category": "history", "answer": "Control - Janet Jackson", "choices": ["True Stories - Talking Heads", "Control - Janet Jackson", "Raising Hell - Run DMC", "True Colors - Cyndi Lauper"] }, { "question": "What southern sitcom, which debuted in 1986, are the following characters from: Julia, Suzanne, Mary Jo, Charlene, Anthony and Bernice?", "category": "history", "answer": "Designing Women", "choices": ["Designing Women", "Mamas Family", "Its A Living", "The Golden Girls"] }, { "question": "This was an attempt to establish the use of the metric system in the United States. However it was not accepted and the US never converted.", "category": "history", "answer": "The 1975 Metric Conversion Act", "choices": ["The 1975 Metric Conversion Act", "IEEE Conversion RFC", "The Common management interface protocol", "ANSI Metric Conversions"] }, { "question": "This suspension bridge collapsed due to resonance - a twisting pattern never seen before, took the bridge down.", "category": "history", "answer": "The Tacoma Narrows Bridge", "choices": ["The John Hancock Bridge", "Willamette River Pedestrian Bridge", "The Tacoma Narrows Bridge", "The Golden Gate Bridge"] }, { "question": "In early 1985 the manufacturer of this drink changed the recipe of the product, but after months of complaints, it was forced by the consumers to restore the original formula.", "category": "history", "answer": "Coca Cola", "choices": ["Coca Cola", "Pepsi", "Yoo-hoo", "Dr. Pepper"] }, { "question": "At the time, this was the most complex ship, employing safety measures unseen before.  She was double-bottomed and separated into 16 watertight compartments. Nevertheless, she sank on her maiden voyage.", "category": "history", "answer": "Titanic", "choices": ["Titanic", "Britanic", "Andrea Doria", "The Empress of Ireland"] }, { "question": "This rap artist, born Stanley Kirk Burrell was known for his lavish tours and catchy hooks.  However, his attempted restyling as a gangsta-rapper was a failure", "category": "history", "answer": "MC Hammer", "choices": ["MC Hammer", "Marky Mark", "Busta Rhymes", "Vanilla Ice"] }, { "question": "This aircraft was proposed by Boeing in the 80s, but never entered production due to excessive noise from its unducted fan engines and high production costs.", "category": "history", "answer": "Boeing 7J7", "choices": ["Spruce Goose flying boat", "Boeing 7J7", "Boeing Business Jet", "Boeing 737"] }, { "question": "This tank was built during World War II, but had weight and speed issues.  It never saw battle.", "category": "history", "answer": "Panzerkampfwagen VIII Maus", "choices": ["Panzerkampfwagen VIII Maus", "Sturmpanzer IV Brummbär", "M3A5 Grant", "Heavy Tank Charron 2C"] }, { "question": "This 15,000 ton, German-built ship maintained a route from Tallinn to Stockholm.  In 1994, it sunk to the bottom of the Baltic Sea due to a badly designed bow door.", "category": "history", "answer": "Estonia Ferry", "choices": ["Estonia Ferry", "Blak Bark of Ostend", "Barge of Calais", "Castor to Circe"] }, { "question": "Three of these political events occurred in the 80s. Which one happened earlier?", "category": "history", "answer": "The Winter of Discontent in the UK", "choices": ["The Collapse of the Soviet Union", "The USA invades Panama", "The Winter of Discontent in the UK", "The Velvet Revolution in Czechoslovakia"] }, { "question": "All of these famous political leaders lost their power in the 80s, except one. Can you spot him?", "category": "history", "answer": "Francois Mitterrand", "choices": ["Augusto Pinochet", "Ceausescu", "Francois Mitterrand", "Gustav Husak"] }, { "question": "The AIDS epidemic was identified and named before 1980.", "category": "history", "answer": "False", "choices": ["True", "False"] }, { "question": "Mel Gibson starred in all of the following four movies. However, only one of them was produced during the 80s.  Which one?", "category": "history", "answer": "Lethal Weapon 2", "choices": ["Forever Young", "Mad Max", "Lethal Weapon 3", "Lethal Weapon 2"] }]